The Melbaney weekly commentary covering
monetary, economic, and geopolitical
news events.
Silver is a different animal. No central
[music] bank buying investor demand in
competition with increasing industrial
demand. Those are the two most critical
elements. And you know, you're dealing
with now a 5-year supply deficit. Five
years in a row supply deficit. It's a
very worthy investment or speculation
even just looking at the supply
dynamics. But again, if you've got
motivation from a demand standpoint, an
investor looking to hedge against
inflation, what [music] have you, what
we tend to see in a rising metals
environment is that silver remains price
accessible far [music] longer than gold.
>> Now, here are Kevin Oric and David
Melaney.
>> Welcome to the Michael Baney weekly
commentary. I'm Kevin Oric along with
David Melaney. David, the call last week
was just great with the guys and that's
still available for our listeners.
>> Yeah, if you missed last week's next
regime playbook, the webinar, there's a
link for you in the show notes and the
presentation is just over an hour 60 to
90 minutes, including some of the early
questions. Interestingly, I've never
seen more questions in Q.
>> What was it over 60?
>> Yeah, you don't have to sit through the
entire Q&A, but I think you'd find
plenty of value in doing so if you could
carve the time out. We had between 60
and 65 questions and that's just amazing
engagement with the ideas and the market
insights we shared. I'd say just don't
miss it. We were talking last night,
Dave, how technology instead of being a
tool can actually be our God, little G
God. And without us even knowing it, and
you're talking about engaging questions,
using technology for people to actually
interact personally is the right way to
use technology instead of AI telling you
what to think and just cumulatively
figuring out what the best answer is.
It's better to engage and sometimes to
disagree.
>> Yeah. a tool towards a particular end.
And meeting as we do on Monday evenings,
you brought up Haidiger's essay, the
question concerning technology.
>> That's a dense essay.
>> It is. And I admit continental
philosophy was always Mary Catherine's
domain.
>> That's why you married her [laughter]
for many reasons.
>> The essay did reach back to the
ancients. So Haidiger was drawing on
Plato and Aristotle, which was always a
relief to me. Is always a relief to me.
All the same, reading Haidiger is like
rolling a tight and tangled ball of
string around in my hands. You see the
complications on the surface, the
touching points and the relationships
and know it's ever more convoluted the
farther in you go. So patience required,
it's complicated, but it was a
worthwhile effort. What I appreciated
most about the essay was the experience
of pushing out the boundaries of my
thinking on technology. Sometimes
particular conclusions are less
important than sort of a broadening of
perspective, an expanding of
intellectual range resulting from a
rigorous mental exercise. I woke up this
morning and I was thinking differently
about everything and not directly tied
but sort of indirectly related to the
essay.
>> One of the things that I liked about the
essay, I mean it's 14 pages of very very
dense thinking. That's why after a
talisker or I do need to go back and
reread it the next morning. But what I
liked about it was he's not pro or
against technology. In fact, he says
that it can rule you either way. What
you need to do is actually ask yourself
what is the essence of the thing? What
is the meaning? What's the larger
picture? And you know, I know you try to
do that with the markets, Dave. So,
let's move to the markets. What is the
meaning right now of what's going on?
Well, no less complicated, but at least
more approachable. We've got an economy
that's running at 4.1% growth rates.
That's the November 17th reading of the
Atlanta GDP now model. And you've got
financial markets which remain amply
supplied with liquidity. So, there's
been certainly up through the beginning
of last week a lot of enthusiasm. The
question is do liquidity dynamics shift
and do we see asset performance shift
lower even while we have healthy
economic statistics?
>> Yeah,
>> many aspects of this ball of string are
easy to see. Some complications and
knots are are closer to the middle and
you can't see them immediately
appreciated only if you're willing to
unravel it a bit further. So under the
surface there's a lot going on in the
last 10 days a number of problems have
emerged. It's I [laughter] have to think
about why you're talking about a ball of
string all knotted up. I had to make a
decision this weekend because I hung
Christmas lights and we have those
lights, you know, that have the little
the icicle strands that hang down and I
was up on the top of the ladder and I
had a tangled mess and I stayed on the
top of the ladder for quite a while
thinking, you know, if I just shake this
thing out long enough, it's going to
happen. And then I realized, you know, I
don't know how many people die trying to
do that every year. Hang their Christmas
lights and try to get them untangled
from the top of the ladder. [laughter]
But I finally I finally came down and I
untangled it. Fortunately for me, I'm
still alive and the lights work. But
let's go back to tangling and
untangling. The tangle that we have
right now is because we've had such
freedom in money. I mean, there's it's
just been loose policy for year after
year after year. That's why there's
liquidity. But right now, the repo
market is starting to show some signs
that people want more interest.
>> And you've got leadership at your top
banks getting together to say we're
probably going to have to address this,
right?
>> And so it's more than a passing concern.
Again, untangling takes time, energy. I
think probably one of the greatest areas
of soul growth for me over the last 15
years is going fly fishing
>> because you do get tangled.
>> Tangled. Yeah. And if you operate too
quickly, if you're trying to resolve the
issue at speed, it just gets worse. You
have to slow down. You have to take your
time.
>> Well, and you said banks are meeting.
I'm going to go back to the banks. Not
only are the banks meeting, but private
credit is a real issue right now, too,
isn't it?
>> For sure. And I think this week, I hear
a growing number of concerned voices in
the private credit space.
>> Makes me think that, you know, again,
some knots are better cut than untied.
There are moments when you're fly
fishing where just cut it off.
>> Let it go. Start over the fly.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um Jeffrey Gundle joins the
choir. He was in a Bloomberg interview
saying the trouble always comes in
financial markets. When people buy
something that they think is safe, it's
sold to them as safe.
>> Mhm.
>> But it's not. M the industry's push to
into retail investors has created the
perfect mismatch between a promise of
liquidity that's backed by illquid
assets. So, you know, making matters
worse, you've got ratings shopping which
has allowed for a lot of private credit
instruments to get an apparent upgrade.
You know, there's competition for the
business, the revenue generated. And so,
these ratings agencies, usually second
tier agencies, it's been intense. They
say, "Oh, it'll be fine. This is a good
asset." When really you can't sell it.
>> Give it an A rating when probably it's
not. Give it a B- rating when it's
clearly not. So, it's not unlike what we
saw during the buildup to the mortgage
crisis in 2008 and 2009 with a number of
those top tier rating agencies giving a
AAA stamp of approval on stuff that was
a flaming bag of dog poop.
>> Chop it up and rebag it basically is
what they did. Yeah. Well, in this
current context, the recommendation from
Gundlac, lots of cash. He's up to 20% of
an allocation uh across portfolios. More
than a little gold. He revised it from
25% to 15.
>> But this is coming from a bond trader,
which I think is the most interesting
bit. Yeah, exactly.
>> As for private credit, we agree with
Jeffrey.
>> Stay away. It's a $1.7 trillion asset
class of lowquality, illlquid assets,
and it's now being offloaded to the
public with dubious ratings acting like
a bathroom air freshener.
>> So, what you're basically saying is if
someone's offering you twice as much
interest as say the US Treasury, you
better watch out because that might be
part of that private credit that's being
sold.
>> Yeah. You're taking more than twice the
risk. So, let's go to private equity,
okay? Which is a little bit different
than being paid interest. This is
actually assets supposedly that are
sellable that you can liquidate. But
that's not necessarily true, is it? No.
The game is to buy a company, take it
private, slice and dice, add a bunch of
debt to the balance sheet, and then
hopefully take your original money out
and make a bunch of money on the pieces
that you sell off.
>> You've got, I think the number was
27,000 unsold companies. So, they were
supposed to be sold and they're past
their date. I mean, you buy them and
sell them and you do all this within a
three to five year time frame
>> and they've been sliced and diced and
broken up into smaller units
>> and they they're not selling in part
because interest rates have moved higher
and the math doesn't work anymore. When
you lever up a balance sheet and then
interest rates move higher on you,
you're in a bit of a pickle. So, I mean,
as you recall, this is the stuff we've
invade against going into insurance
portfolios. For us, the insurance
portfolio today is is a financial
version of a mass grave. Well, quick
recap. Private equities sitting on those
tens of thousands of unsellable
companies. Even though you have mergers
and acquisition activity picking up a
lot and IPO activity, it's really
heating up. They still can't move the
companies, which is telling. To resolve
this, they extend and pretend. They've
got credit services which are provided
through private lenders. basically
private equity launches a new shingle
and says we're also private credit and
they arrange for the financing.
>> So it's almost it's a circle and
basically they're financing themselves
in a way and it's just bad debt.
>> Yeah. And it allows for the limited
partners and the GPS of the private
equity companies to get some of their
money back. But they're again we're
talking about lowquality
illlquid paper that's being stuffed into
unsuspecting portfolios. Not all of it
lands in insurance portfolios, but the
private equity guys have been buying
insurance companies with the benefit of
capturing long-term invested assets that
gives them the allowance to sort of
stuff the private credit into those
portfolios.
>> Well, and we talked about this four or
five years ago when we were at zero
interest rates. We were like, how are
these insurance companies going to
continue to make their minimum interest
payments?
>> They take more risk.
>> Yeah. They're behind the curve. And you
know, I talked to a client yesterday
who's moving money over into a single
IRA, but she had a broker who put her
into seven different annuities in an
IRA. Okay. So, there's a point where you
go, "All right, I mean, we've done
annuities even here at Macanies in the
past when it was appropriate, but right
now you're saying there may be a
danger."
>> Yeah. This would be an excellent time to
avoid buying annuities where private
equity groups have turned policy holders
into bag holders of credit instruments
that no one else in the financial market
will touch with a 10-ft pole. The hope
of course is that when and if credit
concerns arise, there's so much
portfolio opacity with those insurance
assets that your odds of a deposit run
like you could have at a bank, you won't
have a panic because nobody knows what's
in there anyways, right? So looking at
your publicly traded private equity
companies, the performance at
Blackstone, at KKR, at Blue Owl, they're
down 20 to 24% year-to date. That's
notably contrasted with the KBW bank
index and your broker dealers, other
expressions of financial service
providers, which are up 14 to 17% year
to date in line with the S&P. Um, so
banks are hanging in there year to date.
Shadow banks, not so much. So, like I
said, the complicated parts are inside
the ball of string.
>> Well, and it's the stuff you can't see.
I mean, even using that analogy, I'm
glad you brought it back. You cannot
tell where the tangles are often times.
Let's talk about last week, though,
because it was interesting. It had a
spectacular start with some of these
assets like crypto and the tech stocks
that are leading the NASDAQ, but it
didn't finish well. No. And it may well
have been public markets inflection
point.
>> I would say important on two fronts.
You're right. How it started.
Spectacular results earlier in the week,
risk embracement, stellar performance
early on. That's sort of part one only
to be met with mass liquidation later in
the week, which is part two. We're also
getting the 13F reports from hedge funds
which are showing that they're hitting
the exits on a lot of their technology
shares.
>> Do you think that has something to do
with expectations for interest rate cuts
or not? Do you think that's going to
play into it?
>> I think that's becoming a reality. Yeah.
So, we've got minor developments with
major implications and yeah, the
shifting view of interest rates doesn't
seem like much, right? the probability
of a 25 basis point cut in December
except that last week it sunk below 50%.
So odds are increasing that there is no
cut and yet that's what the market has
been counting on. So expectations are
built in. Now you're seeing something of
a disappointment or reversal of
expectations.
>> Well, see that's that tension that the
Fed has all the time. Do you address
inflation or do you address the markets?
And right now inflation, you said it
dropped below 50%. So there is a concern
that inflation's not going away,
>> right? So the pressure is on the Fed.
Maybe they should not be lowering rates.
>> What to prioritize from a monetary
policy perspective, jobs or inflation.
When you're stuck between these two
mandates, they're not always consistent.
And your policy choices, you might have
to look at the trade-offs and choose one
or the other. Well, and these Fed guys
have to be careful what they say because
they can really upset the market.
>> Yeah. Bastic announced his retirement
from the Atlanta Fed in February towards
the end of February. And you know,
following that announcement was
unusually candid thereafter. I think
he's now got nothing to lose. That's
what I would guess. He said that um
forwardlooking indicators suggest
inflation is unlikely to decline
substantially for some time. That raises
concern that inflation expectations
could drift upward and trigger behaviors
which produce higher actual inflation.
The main contributors to elevated
inflation are now services prices other
than housing. Super core services and
core goods prices. So you know Kevin our
takeaway another cut is becoming less
likely
>> right [snorts]
>> and the markets were counting on it.
They were counting on it. That is a
trigger for equity market volatility.
That is a trigger for risk off.
>> Okay. But I wonder too because the Fed
in the past has reacted to the markets
and just thrown inflation out the
window. And you know with these markets
as high as they are, what did you say
this morning? They're three standard
deviations. I mean they're as high as
they've ever been. What is the third
standard deviation? What does that say?
Yeah. If you're looking at a Gaussian
curve, three standard deviations
accounts for 99.95%
of the data. In this case, we're talking
about the time that we've had publicly
traded markets, right? So, there's 0.05%
of all US stock market history where
prices have been higher, valuations have
been higher.
>> So, you're in that 0.00 something.
>> Exactly.
>> But it takes a lot of liquidity to keep
that thing going. And with the
liquidity, it maybe could.
>> Well, and this is where cracks in the
private credit market and what we're
seeing in repo are even more significant
because these are sort of your first
indicators that something is shifting
within the credit markets. While we've
had ample liquidity and while last week
started impressively, it also ended
impressively just in a very dower tone.
So an overvalued market requires
overthe-top
amounts of liquidity to keep the trend
in play. So even a minor curtailment in
liquidity or in this case less cuts less
interest rate cuts that sets the
leveraged speculative liquidity
dependent trader on edge.
>> And and what we've seen with especially
AI stocks is that that liquidity has
been necessary. I mean you've got some
big guys right now cutting back on
Nvidia. Yeah. AI, tech more generally,
the financials, crypto were all under
acute pressure last week. That continues
this week. Soft Bank exited 100% of
their Nvidia position. It was 5.6 5.8
billion, I forget which. Peter Teal, his
hedge fund, uh, they're exiting Nvidia
as well. Notably, these multibillion
dollar holdings sold before Wednesday's
Nvidia earnings report. So, I wonder
why.
>> I wonder what they know. And it may be
that you know we've pressed as much as
we can to the upside $5 trillion market
cap for Nvidia. Is the bloom off the
rose in terms of AI?
>> Well, let me ask on that bloom. Okay,
sometimes you've got a full rose bush,
okay, where you've got roses everywhere.
Today we just have a one concentrated
rose, right? I mean, these markets,
these seven stocks have pretty much
dominated the market. what 25 30% of the
moves have had to do with that or the
capitalization.
>> Yeah. If you look at the percentage
gains in the S&P, I think 40% of the
gains are attributable to those seven
names.
>> So, it could be a concentrated downturn
if that rose gets clipped.
>> That's right. And now you've got Wall
Street pundits scrambling to sort of
reframe and support the narrative.
They're working overtime to convince
investors that they're still early in
the AI trade. I was listening to a
Bloomberg interview uh a guy from
Northern Trust, an analyst from Northern
Trust making the case that AI is very
underinvested.
>> Huh.
>> Wow.
>> Really?
>> Even though they're not making any
profit right now,
>> right? It's underinvested.
>> And Nvidia is making plenty of profits,
but at a $5 trillion market cap, I would
suggest that's a crowded trade, not an
underinvested name. But it's good to
know. Northern Trust thinks uh we're
we're still early in the adoption cycle
for AI. And to be clear, AI has so much
future ahead of it. What's not as clear
if we're investing too much in capacity
today that it'll take a long, long time
to fill.
>> Do you think that's happening with
crypto too? Because crypto is coming
down at the same time, which you had a
good point this morning in our meeting,
Dave. A lot of people treated crypto as
a hedge, almost like a gold, a form of
gold that's just based on a number, but
actually crypto's behavior has been very
much in correlation with the speculative
side of the stock market.
>> Yeah, just with more beta in either
direction. So, it'll outperform on the
upside. If the S&P is doing well, it
does even better. If the S&P is doing
poorly, it does even worse. Bitcoin has
quickly flipped from bullish and
positive year-to- date numbers to
bearish and your smaller
cryptocurrencies have exaggerated those
losses relative to Bitcoin. So, we're
down two 2 and a half% year-to- date
with Bitcoin now, but that's off 27%
from its October 5th peak. You contrast
that with a 56% year-to- date gain in
gold. And yes, it looks like crypto
needs a bullish equity narrative to
grow. It is a risk asset. It's not a
hedge asset. It's not a substitute for
gold or silver. You can own it if you
want, but just know what you own. And I
think even more important, be honest
about why you own it,
>> right?
>> So, well, we talked about that. We
talked about the essence of a thing.
Talking about technology, know the
essence of something. If you ask the
question, we we've talked about this
before. asked the question, would you
own crypto if you knew it wasn't going
to go up? Is there another reason to own
it?
>> And some people have answered that
question with crypto. The way that
Haidiger addresses the issue in his in
his essay, uh what is the purpose? What
is the telos? Is there something that is
being served through this technological
innovation? And it was diversification.
It was decentralization.
>> It actually seems fairly correlated to
risk assets relative to the S&P. that
correlation's picked up considerably
over the last 5 years, just more
volatile in either direction. And I
think the decentralization theme, uh, I
think that narrative has already played
out.
>> So don't mistake it as a hedge and don't
mistake it as private.
>> No, definitely not.
>> Well, and again, to be clear, when we're
talking about AI and we're talking about
the prospects for the price of AI,
you're not saying that it doesn't have a
future. What you're saying is it may be
very, very expensive right now based on
what we're getting out of it,
>> right? And in past cycles of growth and
development, we've seen overinvestment
with something that ultimately was
radically transformative. When we put in
rails across the United States, there
was a boom in rail shares, but there was
also excess. And what in retrospect you
could describe as a bubble, but you
didn't know that you were overbuilding
until people started to say, well,
what's the rate of return on my
investment? And in that moment it was
clear that it was going to be low to
negative because you had built over
capacity. Now we spent the next 50 to 70
years filling that capacity and the
investment ultimately was very
transformative but that did not prevent
investors from being wiped out in the
first phase. You know the bubble turned
to a bust and then post bust then you
had a rebuilding. So you have sort of an
ecstatic gain at first and then you have
a bust and then you have the steady gain
on whether it's practical or not.
>> Yep. So narrative is what we harped on
last week and and the bullish AI
narrative is what seems to now be
unraveling. So financing the
infrastructure buildout providing as we
suggested last week you you've got the
real world obstructions to progress
which are all in the physical world. is
the power that's necessary for the data
centers. It's it's the energy creation.
These are fundamental factors in the
physical world which do not support the
adoption cycle, the time frames, the
expectations for a positive return for
an investor,
>> right?
>> And I think that's where you've got
investors way too far out over the ends
of their skis.
>> You know what it reminds me of? The
other night I was getting my telescope
and a couple of other things out that I
haven't had out in years. And it
requires a lot of battery power. Well,
we didn't have enough double A's. So, I
had all this capacity. I mean, I had I
had Saturn out there. I was just waiting
to go and I didn't have enough double A
power. So, it's interesting how the
physical world sometimes can intrude
that way. But, you know, last week,
Philip talked about the energy sector.
We're talking about that's a little bit
like having batteries, and that's an
undervalued sector right now, isn't it?
>> Yeah. It's a better long-term bet in our
view, the energy aspect. So, bet on
natural gas. Yes. A bet on pipelines to
some degree.
>> Batteries.
>> Yeah, oil. We would include oil.
Although we're slow in putting those
trades in place. I think there's plenty
of time for that to develop. There are
some spillover benefits from AI. But the
energy trade is more fundamentally based
in the underinvestment of the past
decade. Demographic pressures on a
global basis impacting the demand side.
And if you want to look at the supply
dynamics, I would say go to Philip's
section in last week's presentation, the
new regime.
>> We're going to connect that to the show
notes again this week.
>> Exactly. Not everyone agrees on the
energy market supply and demand
dynamics, but he makes a compelling
case. We're in the midst of a rollover
in shale and that is the marginal source
of increase in global supply which with
a clear view on where demand is coming
from that's really the sticking spot is
we're either over supplied or they're
overestimating what is coming online
from shale and in fact if we're losing
production over the next 6 to 12 months
then you've got a price opportunity.
>> Well and let's say we did have the
energy. Let's say we had all the energy
we needed available. We don't have the
grid to run that energy at this point,
do we?
>> No, that's true. The grid doesn't
support what we need for bandwidth, if
you will, or the data centers which put
a lot of pressure on energy supply.
>> So, China though, okay. Do they have the
same constraints that we do?
>> No. And a part of that is they don't
have the limitations we do from the
standpoint of EPA approvals and
permitting. Their cycle of getting
things online is very quick. We saw that
in COVID with the building of hospitals.
What they could do in 30 days would take
us 30 months. And so there is a
constraint that we face that they do not
face. They've also got other factors
like an ample workforce. Some of which
are paid, some of which are not paid,
right?
>> Not paid adequately. Yeah. Slave labor
is an amazing thing when it comes down
to it. Not an advocate. Just saying.
>> Ammunition. Yeah. The Russians or the
Chinese. Yeah. They can make ammunition
like mad. Well, but what we saw last
week uh interesting comments from
Patrick Puan. He's the CEO of total
energy total. He was sharing at the
COP30 the climate summit. I think it's
worth restating that there is a
realistic scenario where global oil and
gas demand continues to rise for the
next 25 years. The assumption has been
actually because of electrification,
because of a move towards renewables
that we were within a few years of peak
demand for oil. What he's saying and
what he's refraraming is that actually
there's a good case to be made that
that's two and a half decades out. Um
that was not a welcome message at the
COP30 summit where the hope is, you
know, the complete abandonment of fossil
fuels.
>> Yeah. So, not only the electrification
of AI, there's a commonality right now
what we're talking about and how it ties
to energy. We do get grid upgrades.
Let's let's assume we get the grid
upgrades. We're going to need not only
coal and oil, but nuclear. I mean,
they're going to be reaching in places
that they haven't really been reaching
up to this point.
>> Yeah. And I think that's where there's a
commonality if you're looking at
electrification and the goals of the
COP30 summit uh and AI. the the
commonality is this desperate need for
grid upgrades, right? And an increase in
energy supplies. When we think about
energy, when we think about consistent
delivery of kilowatts, where are we
going to get it? It is gas. It is
nuclear. It is oil to the extent that a
transition towards electrification is
decades, not years away. So to one
degree or another, those spaces have
been underallocated to by the investment
community, underowned for the past
decade. The growth constraints to AI,
they're all physical world problems.
It's created power. That's the whole
idea behind hard assets.
>> The whole hard asset thesis is that the
world really does exist. There are
constraints and if you invest in the
things that are going to be scarce,
it'll pay.
>> Yeah. And this is where a few years ago
when the green energy revolution was the
front of mind for everybody and
electrification was the inevitability.
This is sort of before the AI narrative.
We had the green energy revolution
narrative.
>> The question we were asking is so how
much copper do we actually need for that
to take place and one view was that we
had to have five times current
production from copper mines to meet
electrification goals on the time frames
you know laid out. There's no ability to
do that. When you start looking at how
those mines, particularly the ones in
Chile, have been managed or state-owned
mines mismanaged, you can't increase
productivity at those mines by more than
5 10 15% in a great year. Yeah.
>> Let alone 500% in a short period of
time. So we looked at it and we thought
this is political. This has nothing to
do with what is actually achievable. the
constraints are in the physical world
and the limiting factor is the current
supplies of product that they have to
have to make it happen.
>> So this sounds very obvious and you
probably didn't have to go to the grants
conference to hear this, but you
basically sell what's abundant and you
buy what's scarce right now in the
markets. Dave, what would you consider
abundant? What what is abundant?
>> At the October grants conference, that
was one of the themes by one of the
speakers. sell assets that are in an
abundant supply and he was basically
making the case against government bonds
and buy what is scarce and he could have
been on our new regime playbook call
last week. I mean that's the case that
we're making.
>> So you're saying the abundance is in the
debt instruments. It's in the bonds.
>> Absolutely. In all forms but
particularly government debt, scarce
assets, hard assets, the most attractive
still being gold.
>> Goldman Sachs who still sees $4,900 by
the end of next year. So 2026 add $1,000
to the current price. What they noted in
their recent comments is a growing
competition between retail ETF buying
going toe-to-toe with the continued
central bank buying and we have not had
that yet. We
>> the retail investor hasn't been abundant
but the central bank buying has been.
>> Yeah. So one or the other shows up to
purchase and you know the verdict is
out. Is it sufficient to tip the scales?
Scarcity and supply and demand dynamics
driving the price higher. When both sets
of buyers are enthusiastically in the
market, that's when prices move and
frankly move faster than most people
expect. One of the things that's been
obvious, especially over the last 10
years, has been how China has under
reported the amount of gold that they've
purchased. I mean, we see it in the
markets. If you remember April of 2013,
I'll never forget it when gold lost $100
on that Friday, April 12th, and then
another $100 on Monday, April 15th. We
wondered where that gold went when it
came out of that ETF, the GLD ETF. But
700 tons ended up in China. That they
under report, don't they?
>> They do under reportport. Yeah. 2013
2014 was very interesting because you
had flows of gold coming out of London
going to Zurich being reprocessed into
bars which were then shipped to Hong
Kong and Shanghai and that product will
never reemerge. The under reportporting
aspect is always something that's
difficult to put your finger on. To what
degree are they under reporting? How
much buying is being done quietly and
not officially reported?
>> How much gold do you have in that back
room?
>> Yeah. Right. The Financial Times article
last week, absolutely worth reading,
titled, "Chinese secretive gold
purchases help fuel record rally."
They're willing to step out on the limb
and take a guess at it. They suggested
that China's unreported gold purchases
could be 10 times the official figures.
>> 10 times?
>> Yeah. So, officially, they're on track
for 24 25 tons this year. Okay. Society
General estimates based on trade data
that by year end the number is closer to
250 tons. So again 10 times what the
official reports are saying. The
Japanese or the Japan bullion markets
association they believe that Chinese
reserves in total not just one year's
demand but in total are now about 5,000
tons. Double what is officially
disclosed. So the world gold council
says that in the most recent quarter
only a third of official buying this is
not just China but all central banks
only a third is being publicly reported
down from 90% four years ago.
>> Okay. So we know but I'm going to ask
the question again. What would be the
reasons for buying right now? If you're
a central bank or you're a retail
investor, what are the reasons?
>> Yeah, I mean gold is this unique asset.
This is where it does so stand out from
Bitcoin or or other alternatives as an
asset class. Hedging and insurance I
think remain sort of the biggest reasons
to own it. Uh policy uncertainty, bond
market pressures, these are things that
are emerging and are now a motivation
for investors as well. So central banks
are hedging but they're not really
concerned about equity market
volatility. Investors have to look and
say okay so what kind of hedges do we
need? Is it a dollar hedge? Is it a
currency hedge? If you're in
>> geopolitical hedge,
>> a geopolitical hedge. Is it a public
policy hedge? These are all relevant
factors. But equity market volatility is
one other thing that gold serves as a
hedge for. The overlap in interests with
these two dynamic sources of demand are
covering dollar risk. There's overlap
there, right?
>> And insulating from geopolitical risk.
There's overlap there. And it doesn't
take much soothing in terms of a daily
paper to see that geopolitical risk is
very real. Sure,
>> we haven't talked about it a lot, but
the current kurluffle between India and
Pakistan worth keeping an eye on.
>> They're close to war and it's just one
more hot bed if you will, one more hot
zone. So we expect these themes to
develop further over the next several
years and for these demand sources both
the investor and the central bank to
pick up the pace of buying.
>> So in that particular case those
overlaps really don't have anything to
do with price they have everything to do
with protection. But let's talk about
the silver market for a moment because
as much as we've been focusing on gold
silver's outperforming this year
>> yeah silver is a different animal. no
central bank buying stuff. Investor
demand in competition with increasing
industrial demand. Those are the two
most critical elements. And you know,
you're dealing with now a fiveyear
supply deficit. Five years in a row
supply deficit. It's a very worthy
investment or speculation even just
looking at the supply dynamics. But
again, if you've got motivation from a
demand standpoint, an investor looking
to hedge against inflation, what have
you, what we tend to see in a rising
metals environment is that silver
remains price accessible far longer than
gold. And that's to your average
investor. Again, being driven on a more
exaggerated basis by retail buyers in
part because the market of silver is so
much smaller than that of gold.
>> And it's a thin market, isn't it? Let's
just look at how much money has gone
into silver ETFs versus gold and look at
the performance.
>> Yeah, and I have to look back at my
notes from a few weeks ago, but we
talked about the silver ETFs having
about 2 billion in inflows if memory
serves correctly. That's year to date,
whereas the gold ETFs have closer to 64
billion year to date.
>> So like 30 times the amount of flow into
gold,
>> right? And yet year to date, gold is up
56%, silver is up 73%. a much smaller
market and more dynamic moves in either
direction
looking ahead and I am hopeful that we
have a further correction in the metals
not guaranteed over the next two weeks
we'll have two different technical views
on the metals and the markets as well
more broadly but talking to Michael
Oliver next week and then the folks from
Elliot Wave just to get differing
perspectives differing wave counts they
look at things using a different model
but still from a technical perspective,
right?
>> But let's get past a potential
correction in the price of gold and
silver. Love to see $3,400 gold. Love to
see 42 $43 silver. That's not
guaranteed.
>> But in the company's history, we've seen
silver at $50 twice in the past or close
to $50 twice in the past. Do you think
50 is actually going to be a number that
we not just fall from, but we rise from
from here on out?
>> Well, and that's what I'm getting at. 50
is a new generational floor.
>> We have a new price regime being made
and not many in the markets today
imagine the prices that we could see.
>> Well, you were on an interview last week
that the person who interviewed you
could not believe that you were even
calling for 65 bucks.
>> Yeah. Incredulous that in 2026 we could
see silver at over $65 an ounce. So, I
did wonder at the time if she
appreciated, you know, again going back
to that 5year supply deficit. These
things do happen. I mean, we've actually
had outperformance even relative to gold
and silver. We've had up to 80% gains in
platinum this year, and that's on the
basis of a three-year supply deficit.
>> Right. And central banks are not
involved in silver, platinum, or
palladium.
>> No, but those fundamental factors can be
ignored for long periods of time, and
then there is a catchup. There's a
ratchet in price. And I think that is
what we're likely to see this five-year
supply deficit and a general recognition
that there's not as much that can be
purchased really at any reasonable
price.
>> So again, I wondered if the host on that
show was aware of the 5-year supply
deficit. And I did also wonder if she's
been sort of drinking the Fed Kool-Aid
on inflation being largely resolved. I
mean, setting aside Bostic's comments,
the general consensus is, you know,
we're moving closer to our 2% target.
We're not quite there yet, but you guys
get ready to retire, right? Like Bostic,
but okay. So, you have said over the
last few weeks, and I really like the
way you're thinking that the metals,
gold is expensive right now, but it's
underowned. Would you say the same thing
about the other metals?
>> Yeah, expensive at these levels, but
very underowned. and platinum and
palladium would be even more to the
point. And those markets are even
thinner still relative to silver. Those
white metals trade really hot, white hot
in part because they're so small.
>> You know, I think a good test, Dave, you
brought this up in the meeting this
morning before we came in here. A good
test to find out whether gold and silver
is underowned is coming up because a lot
of people are going to be with people
coming up here on Thanksgiving,
Christmas, people that they don't
normally see. It would be worth asking,
hey, do you own any or how much do you
own?
>> Yeah. Ask your friends, ask your family
over for Thanksgiving. What percentage
of their portfolio is invested in
anything precious metals related? How
many ounces of gold or silver do they
personally own? How has your financial
adviser framed that year-to-ate gains in
precious metals? Are they still
discouraging these types of allocations?
Gather your anecdotal data over the
Thanksgiving holiday. Come back, share
what you find in the commentary comments
section. I'm curious what you find. I
think there's going to be plenty of
supporting. And again, just it's
anecdotal, but how many people do you
know who actually have a significant
stake in the medals already?
>> Well, and you know, the answer to the
question, one of the things that I've
loved about doing this with your family
for the last 38 years is the narrative
hasn't changed. I mean the price has the
narrative hasn't changed. We talk about
having an allocation as a percentage for
preservation and insurance in any
portfolio in any time period. So to be
honest with you, if somebody at the
family table doesn't have any gold,
there's an allocation problem, not a
decision problem on the price.
>> Well, and this is what has made the
allocation strategy now being suggested
by the chief investment officer at
Morgan Stanley so interesting. the 60 20
60% stocks 20% bonds 20% gold that
becomes compelling. Back in the late 60s
early 70s my dad ran the data on sort of
an optimal portfolio allocation. If your
object is growth growth oriented
>> 75% stocks 25% gold was the
recommendation.
>> We reran the number back tested the data
in recent years and it's within a few
percentage points of that.
>> Yeah. And basically, if you had a 7525%
allocation and did an annual rebalance
in years where you've got significant
draw downs in equities, you've got
liquid dry powder to lower your cost
basis in those equity positions versus
the 100% equity owner who then has to
just sit tight and play the patients
game and listen to their financial
advisor say, "Well, you can't time the
markets. You can't." No, but you can be
better positioned. And I think portfolio
construction is where most of your
long-term gains will ultimately come
from. If you have yet to position in
metals, I highly recommend you talk to
one of our adviserss. Is it's the
allocations and it's the portfolio
construction which are the most
important choice you can make assuming
you've already decided to own the
metals.
>> Well, and then you also dollar cost
average Dave. I mean I do too. Every two
weeks I buy a little and you buy a
little as an addition to the allocation.
>> I just checked my inbox. I own more gold
and silver as of this morning. I use our
vault plan. It allocates money from
every paycheck to the metals. So
currently I'm positioned and have it set
up to buy 70% silver, 30% gold.
>> Those ratios do change more towards
50/50 or even 7030 the other direction
favoring gold.
>> And that's what you're adding. That's
not your allocation.
>> That's right. Exactly. That's how I'm
adding given that the ratio is so much
in favor of silver today,
>> but getting personalized advice is what
you can expect from our adviserss. And I
think I would just encourage you here
and now to fully engage. I know the
holidays are coming. We've got
Thanksgiving, Christmas shortly to
follow, but I think we're at a
significant inflection point in the
financial markets and it is a time to be
fully engaged.
>> You've been listening to the Melvey
weekly commentary. I'm Kevin Oric along
with David Melaney. You can find us at
mlvaney.com
mcalvany.com
and you can call us anytime at
800525-9556.
[music]
This has been the MacBainy weekly
commentary. The views expressed should
not be considered to be a solicitation
or a recommendation for your investment
portfolio. You should consult a
professional financial adviser to assess
your suitability for risk and
investment. Join us again [music] next
week for a new edition of the Mulaney
Weekly commentary.
[music]